Guide to the Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Browning Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Browning collection
1835-1906
1850-1889
GEN MSS 839
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.63
(7 boxes) + 1 broadside folder + 1 object storage item
The Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Browning collection is a mixed-provenance collection of material by and related to Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Browning. Series I, Robert Browning Papers, contains a few manuscripts by him, as well as many letters, most written after 1870. Recipients include Mrs. Bayne; Isabel Jane Blagden; Moncure Conway; Charles Deschamps; Frank Hill; William Charles Macready; Felix Moscheles, and William Wetmore Story. Letters to Browning include an extensive series of literary letters from J. D. Williams, as well as letters from Sophia Ann Landor and Amelia Ann Blanford Edwards. The series also contains a few photographs of the Brownings, and artwork and a commonplace book by Browning's father, Robert Browning (1781-1866). Series II, Elizabeth Barrett Browning Papers, contains manuscripts and correspondence. Manuscripts include autograph drafts of Casa Guidi Windows; Last Poems; Poems and Sonnets; and The Runaway Slave at Pilgrim's Point. Corrrespondence includes letters to Hugh Stuart Boyd, Cornelius Mathews, Mary Russell Mitford and John Ruskin; the collection also contains letters from Harriet Martineau to Barrett Browning (housed in a scrapbook in Box 8).
Browning, Robert, 1812-1889
Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861
General note
Many items in elaborate late nineteenth and early twentieth century collectors' bindings.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources between 1932 and 1991, as noted on individual folders or on the catalog cards included with the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Robert Browning (1812-1889)
Robert Browning, one of the most influential Victorian poets, was born into an Evangelical family in Camberwell in South London. Educated largely at home, Browning as a young man read and traveled widely. His father subsidized his first, relatively unsuccessful publications, including several plays and the much-ridiculed long poem Sordello (1840).
In 1845 he met the more successful and popular poet Elizabeth Barrett (1806-1861); they eloped in September, 1846 and moved to Italy, where they spent the next fifteen years, mainly in Florence and Asolo. Browning published Men and Women, the collection of dramatic monologues that are now among his best-known works, in 1855. Following his wife's death in Florence in 1861, Browning returned to London and became a member of London's literary circles. Dramatis Personae appeared in 1864. Four years later, The Ring and the Book, Browning's longest and most ambitious work, was published, and was both very popular and critically acclaimed.
In his later years, Browning traveled often, returning to Italy for several visits with his son "Pen" (Robert Wiedemann Barrett Browning). "Browning Societies," reading groups that met to discuss and promote Browning's works and philosophy, were founded throughout England and the United States during the 1880s. Robert Browning died at his son's home, Ca' Rezzonico in Venice, on December 12, 1889.
Elizabeth Barrett Browning (1806-1861)
Elizabeth Barrett Browning, popular Victorian poet, was born in England to prosperous landowning parents and spent most of her childhood and adolescence at Hope End, the family's 500-acre estate in Herfordshire. Educated at home, Barrett began writing poetry when very young and continued to write despite frequent ill-health, publishing three collections in the 1830s as well as popular Abolitionist poems, including The Runaway Slave at Pilgrim's Point.
After she moved with her family to London in 1838, Elizabeth was introduced to several literary figures, including Mary Russell Mitford, who became a close friend and mentor. Her health worsened, however, and by 1841 she was mostly confined to her upstairs room at 50 Wimpole Street. Her 1842 poem The Cry of the Children raised support for one of the first child labor laws; her collection of Poems, which appeared two years later, was a great popular and critical success.
It was also the occasion of her meeting Robert Browning, who sent her an admiring letter; the two met in 1845, and carried on a year-long courtship before eloping in September, 1846. During this time, she wrote the now-famous Sonnets from the Portuguese. On hearing of her marriage, her father disinherited her, and the two never spoke again. The Brownings moved to Italy shortly after their honeymoon, settling in Florence. There, Elizabeth's health improved, and in 1849 she gave birth to the couple's only child, Robert Wiedemann Barrett Browning ("Pen").
Browning continued to write and to publish. In addition to several collections of poems, in 1851 she published Casa Guidi Windows, a longer poem which expressed her passionate support for the Italian Risorgimento. Aurora Leigh, her "novel-poem" narrating the emotional and intellectual development of a woman poet, was published in 1856. It was extremely popular; nineteen editions appeared before 1885, and it was admired by many contenporaries, including George Eliot, Emily Dickinson, and Susan B. Anthony, for its outspokenness on the condition of women and the sexual "double standard."
Elizabeth's health failed rapidly after 1857. Her last publication, Poems Before Congress (1860), again exrpressed her support for the Italian revolutionaries and criticized the British for not coming to their aid. It was not well received in England. Elizabeth Barrett Browning died in Casa Guidi, Florence, on June 29, 1861. Her posthumous Last Poems were published by Robert Browning in 1862.
Scope and Contents
The Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Browning Collection is a mixed-provenance collection of material by and related to Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Browning. Series I, Robert Browning Papers, contains a few manuscripts by him, as well as many letters, most written after the death of Elizabeth. Recipients include Mrs. Bayne; Isabel Jane Blagden; Moncure Conway; Charles Deschamps; Frank Hill; William Charles Macready; Felix Moscheles, and William Wetmore Story. Letters to Browning include an extensive series of literary letters from J. D. Williams, as well as letters from Sophia Ann Landor and Amelia Ann Blanford Edwards.The series also contains a few photographs of the Brownings, and artwork and a commonplace book by Browning's father, Robert Browning (1781-1866).
Series II, Elizabeth Barrett Browning Papers, contains manuscripts and correspondence. Manuscripts include autograph drafts of Casa Guidi Windows; Last Poems; Poems and Sonnets; and The Runaway Slave at Pilgrim's Point. Corrrespondence includes letters to Hugh Stuart Boyd, Cornelius Mathews, Mary Russell Mitford and John Ruskin; the collection also contains letters from Harriet Martineau to Barrett Browning (housed in an album in Box 8).
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Robert Browning Papers, 1835-1906. II. Elizabeth Barrett Browning Papers, 1838-1861.
Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; English drama -- 19th century; English literature -- 19th century; English poetry -- 19th century; Women authors; Bindings (gathered matter components) -- 19th century; Bindings (gathered matter components) -- 20th Century; Commonplace books -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Drawings (visual works) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Scrapbooks -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Blagden, Isa, 1816-1873; Boyd, Hugh Stuart, 1781-1848; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907; Deschamps, Charles William, 1848-1908; Edwards, Amelia B., 1831-1892; Hill, Frank Harrison, 1830-1910; Landor, Sophia Ann; Macready, William Charles, 1793-1873; Martineau, Harriet, 1802-1876; Mathews, Cornelius, 1817-1889; Mitford, Mary Russell, 1787-1855; Moscheles, Felix, 1833-1917; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Story, William Wetmore, 1819-1895; Williams, J. D., Rev.
- Robert Browning Papers, 1835-1906; Series I; 2.79; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into five subseries: Catalog Cards, containing copies of the catalog cards for many items in the series; Manuscripts, alphabetically arranged. Letters by Robert Browning is alphabetically arranged by recipient, followed by letter books and albums containing multiple letters by and to both Robert and Elizabeth Barrett Browning. These are followed by Letters by Others, alphabetically arranged by correspondent; and Other Material, which is unarranged.
  Scope and Contents
  Contents include a manuscript copy of A Blot in the 'Scutcheon annotated by Browning and the actor William Macready, and letters to numerous correspondents, including Isabel Jane Blagden, Frank Hill, Felix Moscheles, George Smith, and William Wetmore Story. The letter albums contain letters from Browning to Charles Deschamps, William Macready, Elizabeth Clementine Dodge Kinney, and George Knox Gillespie. Letters by other correspondents include an extensive series of literary letters from J. D. Williams, as well as letters to Browning from Sophia Ann Landor and Amelia Ann Blanford Edwards. (The albums also contain letters to and from Elizabeth Barrett Browning.)
  Other Material includes a number of autographs; pictorial material; a commonplace book and drawings by Robert Browning's father, Robert Browning (1781-1866); and Browning's stationery case.
  - Catalog Cards (Box 1)
    - Catalog cards, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts
    - A Blot in the 'Scutcheon: manuscript copy by Sarianna Browning, annotated by Robert Browning and William Macready, 1842, 1884 (Box 1)
    - Paracelsus: Browning's copy of the first edition (1835), with extensive annotations by him in preparation for the 1849 edition, 1835, undated (Box 1)
      General note
      Tinker 408
    - Wagner gave six concerts: autograph manuscript, signed, of a four-line stanza, 1877 May 21 (Box 1)
  - Letters by Robert Browning
    - Letter: to William Allingham, 1858 November 8 (Box 2)
      Accompanied by a note from Elizabeth Barrett Browning
    - Letter: to Madame Belloc, 1881 March 18 (Box 2)
    - Letter: in the third person to Messrs. Bimell and Son, 1886 March 3 (Box 2)
    - Letters: to Isabel Jane Blagden..., 1859-1868, undated; 3 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Gerald Blunt..., 1881 March 16 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Robert ("Pen") Browning, 1871 October 17 (Box 2)
    - Letters: to Moncure Conway, 1868, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to John W. Field, 1881 December 20 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Frederick Gard Fleay, 1887 July 20 (Box 2)
    - Letters: to Charles S. Francis, 1856-1860 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Frederick J. Furnivall, 1885 November 17 (Box 2)
      Accompanied by two envelopes.
    - Letter: to Alexander B. Grosart, 1875 February 24 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Miss Haworth, [1844?] (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Miss Haworth, 1847 June 29 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Emily Hickey, 1883 July 20 (Box 2)
    - Letters: to Emily Hickey, 1887 (Box 2)
    - Letters: to Frank Hill, 1884-1885 (Box 2)
      Concerning the 1843 production of A Blot on the 'Scutcheon.
      Accompanied by letters to Mrs. Frank Hill, 1885 March and 1885 April.
    - Letter: to George Stillman Hillard, 1875 March 1 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to John Edwin Howard, 1884 February 1 (Box 2)
      Accompanied by a copy of Howard's marriage certificate, 1890; his death certificate, 1897 June 28, and a printed obituary
    - Letter: to Anna Brownell Murphy Jameson, 1847 April 1 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Mr. Kingsland, 1877 November 10 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Charles Kingsley, 1867 July 13 (Box 2)
      Accompanied by photograph of Browning inscribed to Kingsley, 1867.
    - Letter: to Mrs. Kinney, 1871 January 6 (Box 2)
    - Letters: to the Reverend Robert E. Landor, 1864 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Miss Lewis, 1886 November 16 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Mrs. Lewis, 1876 May 9 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Mrs. Lippincott, 1875 June 28 (Box 2)
    - Letters: to Lady Cecil Chetwynd-Talbot, Marchioness of Lothian, 1867 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Samuel Lucas, 1860 January 17 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to William Charles Macready, 1837 June 15 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Mrs. Matthews, 1863 April 22 (Box 2)
    - Letters: to Felix Moscheles, 1867-1889 (Box 2)
      Volume containing six letters on the subjects of art and literature, with a copy of a poem by Anacreon in Browning's hand, and a translation by him.
    - Letter: to Felix Moscheles, 1887 November 30 (Box 2)
      Contains Browning's translation of Horace, Sermones I.2.11
      Accompanied by a facsimile of the letter.
    - Letter: to Lord Mount-Temple, 1887 April 2 (Box 2)
      Accompanied by small pen-and-ink sketch.
    - Letter: to Dante Gabriel Rossetti, 1855 October 23 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to John Ruskin, 1856 October 3 (Box 2)
    - Letter: to Richard Herne Shepherd, 1867 February 1 (Box 2)
    - Letters: to George Smith, 1873 (Box 2)
      Concerning the legal aspects of Red Cotton Night-Cap Country.
      Accompanied by a letter from John Duke Cambridge to Browning, annotated by Browning, 1873 March 26; and the manuscript of the Advertisement to the poem.
    - Letter: to Gordon Smith, 1877 January 16 (Box 2)
    - Letters: to Edith Story, 1865, 1872; 2 (Box 2)
      Includes one letter signed by "Pen" Browning.
    - Letter: to Mrs. William Story, undated (Box 3)
    - Letters: to William Wetmore Story, 1861-1864, 1884 (Box 3)
    - Letter: to Mrs. Ward, 1887 November 30 (Box 3)
    - Letters: to Helen Zimmern, 1876-1882 (Box 3)
    - Letter: to "Sir John", 1863 May 21 (Box 3)
    - Letter: to "Powell", undated (Box 3)
    - Letter: to an unidentified recipient, 1875 June 16 (Box 3)
    - Letter: to an unidentified recipient, 1880 December 18 (Box 3)
    - Letter: to an unidentified recipient, 1885 April 5 (Box 3)
    - Letter: to an unidentified recipient, undated (Box 3)
    - Album of letters by Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Browning, 1835-1889, undated (Box 3)
      Contents include 17 letters from Robert Browning to Mrs. Bayne; 9 letters from Robert Browning to Charles Deschamps; 5 letters from Robert Browning to William Charles Macready; and 2 letters by Elizabeth Barrett Browning.
      The album also includes portraits of both Brownings and of several recipients.
    - Autograph Letters of Elizabeth B. Barrett and Robert Browning, 1844-1889, undated (Box 3)
      Contents include 3 letters from Robert Browning to Elizabeth Clementine Dodge Kinney, and 4 letters from Elizabeth Barrett Browning to her; single letters from Robert Browning to George Knox Gillespie and Thomas Hutchinson; and a letter from Elizabeth Barrett Browning to Sophia Cotterell.
      The album also includes portraits of both Brownings.
    - T.B.I.Y.T.B--The Pundits to William Lyon Phelps, June 18, 1933, 1841-1889, undated (Box 4)
      Case containing 13 autograph letters by Robert Browning, including letters to Isa Blagden, Miss Hickey, and William Charles Macready; an autograph excerpt from The Founder of the Feast; and 2 letters and a fragment by Elizabeth Barrett Browning.
  - Letters by Others
    - Autographs. Browning. Correspondence, 1844-1889, undated
      Large album containing letters to Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Browning. Contents include 61 letters and 11 autograph manuscripts sent by J. D. Williams to Robert Browning; 9 letters from Elizabeth Sophia Landor to Robert Browning; 9 letters from Amelia Ann Blanford Edwards to Robert Browning; 7 letters from the Earl of Carnarvon to Robert Browning; and 11 Harriet Martineau letters sent to Elizabeth Barrett Browing in 1844 and 1845. In addition, the album contains many single letters addressed to Robert Browning; portraits, photographs and illustrations; biographical sketches and other descriptive material; and an auction catalog. For complete information, consult the card set that accompanies the volume.
    - Letter: Browning, Fannie Barrett to Miss Harris, undated (Box 4)
    - Letters: Browning, Robert Wiedemann to William Lyon Phelps, 1904, 1906 (Box 4)
    - Letters: Browning, Sarianna to Miss Harris, 1894 (Box 4)
    - Letters: Paul, Charles Kegan to Robert Browning, 1883 (Box 4)
  - Other Material
    - Autrograph address book kept by Robert Browning, undated (Box 4)
    - Autograph inscription in Greek from Plato's Republic, undated (Box 4)
    - Autographs, clipped from letters, undated (Box 4)
    - Autographs of Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Browning, 1861 (Box 4)
      Daggett autograph collection
    - Corrections and notes in Browning's hand in Thomas Powell's A Dream of Arcady, 1848 (Box 4)
    - Portraits, photographs, and caricatures of Robert Browning, undated (Box 4)
      Accompanied by a photograph of Elizabeth Barrett Browning and a photograph of a room in Casa Guidi.
    - Views of Camberwell and Hatcham, undated (Box 4)
    - Browning, Robert, 1781-1866: commonplace book, undated (Box 4)
    - Browning, Robert, 1781-1866: original drawing with note, undated (Box 4)
    - Browning, Robert, 1781-1866: collection of 50 pen, pencil and ink sketches, undated (Box 4)
    - Browning, Robert: wooden stationery case containing blank stationery printed with Browning's address: 29, DeVere Gardens, W., undated (Box 5 Object storage)
- Elizabeth Barrett Browning Papers, 1838-1861; Series II; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Catalog Cards, containing copies of the catalog cards for many items in the series; Manuscripts, alphabetically arranged; and Letters by Elizabeth Barrett Browning, alphabetically arranged by recipient.
  Contents include autograph drafts of Casa Guidi Windows, Last Poems, and Poems and Sonnets ;as well as letters to Hugh Stuart Boyd, Thomas Carlyle, Cornelius Mathews, and John Ruskin. Other letters by and to Elizabeth Barrett Browning, including letters to Clementine Dodge Kinney and letters from Harriet Martineau, are located in the letter albums in Boxes 3 and 8 of this collection.
  - Catalog Cards
    - Catalog cards, undated (Box 6)
  - Manuscripts
    - Carlyle: autograph manuscript by Elizabeth Barrett Browning and H. H. Horne, undated (Box 6)
    - Casa Guidi Windows, Part I: autograph manuscript, 1850-1851 (Box 6)
      This draft is titled A Meditation in Tuscany.
    - Casa Guidi Windows, Part II: autograph manuscript, 1850-1851 (Box 6)
      This draft is titled Casa Guidi Windows, second Part.
    - Last Poems: autograph manuscript, 1850-1861 (Box 6)
      Accompanied by typed list of contents.
    - Loved Once: autograph manuscript, [1844?] (Box 6)
    - Notebook containing drafts of poems and paraphrases in the hand of Elizabeth Barrett Browning, 1849-1861 (Box 6)
    - Poems and Sonnets: autograph manuscripts, 1838-1850 (Box 6)
    - The Runaway Slave at Pilgrim's Point: autograph manuscript, 1846-1847 (Box 6)
    - A Sabbath on the Sea: autograph manuscript, signed, [1845?] (Box 7)
    - Stanzas Addressed to Miss Landon, Suggested by Her Stanzas on the Death of Mrs. Hemans: autograph manuscript, signed with initials and addressed to Leticia Elizabeth Landon ("L.E.L."), 1835 November 7 (Box 7)
  - Letters by Elizabeth Barrett Browning
    - Letter: extract, in another hand, to Isabella Jane Blagden, undated (Box 7)
    - Letter: to Hugh Stuart Boyd, 1843 December 12 (Box 7)
      Lengthy letter on subjects including the idea for A Dream of Exile; Ossian; and animal magnetism. Bound with a portrait of Elizabeth Barrett Browning and a lock of her hair.
    - Letter: to Hugh Stuart Boyd, undated (Box 7)
    - Letter: to Madame Braun, [1860] (Box 7)
    - Letters: to Thomas Carlyle, 1844 August (Box 7)
    - Letter: to R. H. Horne, 1843 July 13 (Box 7)
    - Letter: to Anna Brownell Jameson, undated (Box 7)
      Tinker 396.
    - Letters: to James Jackson Jarves, 1856-1857, undated (Box 7)
      Accompanied by a carte de visite of Elizabeth Barrett Browning and her son ("Pen").
    - Letter: to John Kenyon, [before 1845] (Box 7)
    - Letter: to Cornelius Mathews, 1845 April 30 (Box 7)
      Lengthy letter mentioning her correspondence with Robert Browning; Thomas Hood's illness; and Harriet Martineau and Miss Mitford.
    - Letter: to Mary Russell Mitford, [1851] September 24 (Box 7)
    - Letter: to John Ruskin, [1859?] May 1 (Box 7)
    - Letter: in the third person, to Messrs. Saunders and Oakley, undated (Box 7)
    - Letter: in French, to an unidentified recipient, undated (Box 7)
    - Letter: fragment, signed, undated (Box 7)
  - Oversize
    - Autographs. Browning. Correspondence, 1844-1889, undated (Box 8 Oversize)
    - View of Camberwell and caricature of Robert Browning, undated (Box 9 Broadside folder)